I think he both confirmed what I thought he would be like and also added something
really quite different.
I knew he would be, to some extent, slightly intimidating because he was such a
powerful intellect and he was such a powerful physical presence.
And he didn't suffer falls.
But also he came across as being extremely sympathetic and interested.
And interested in me as then a young writer. I was spanning between the worlds of
academic world, architectural history and journalism.
Cedric was interested in what I was doing, what I was interested in, and what I knew
about.
And that generosity, that inquisitiveness, I think, came across very strongly,
more strongly than the fact that he was actually quite a formidable figure.
So I liked him immediately.
I thought I probably would, but I was also slightly nervous about meeting him.
He certainly had a very strong physical presence.
His appearance was very cultivated.
He always wore a stiff white collar.
He generally wore a black string knitted tie and often a black shirt,
sometimes a light-coloured jacket.
He was a big man, you know, he was my sort of build.
He had a very powerful voice that he could make carry.
He was theatrical, he could be quite a good mimic.
He was a very good raconteur.
You knew when he walked in a room.
And he had that sort of charisma, that sort of presence,
which was that of a performer and that of someone who had something to say.
There was, and there still are, many things that Cedric said that still resonate in
my head.
There are phrases which sound simple but are actually incredibly complicated.
And one of them is calculated uncertainty constructed.
And if you think of those three words, they are, each of them, very precise.
And you put them together and you get an extraordinary combination of meanings.
But actually for Cedric, that was very, very precise.
that it was you could build something architecture was not a futile act you
could calculate something so you could design you could predict you could think
about the future and obviously you had to deal with uncertainty you don't know
what's going to happen in the future you certainly don't know everything that's
going to happen in the future so whatever you do your calculations have
to take into account uncertainty so there are phrases like that which
sometimes to me are very useful even if they might be applied in very different
Delight, I think, was a very important term for Cedric. He used it in a number of
different ways, and I think there are two in particular that I would mention.
One is the translation of Vitruvius' text on architecture into English by a man
called Henry Wotton in the early 17th century.
It rendered commoditas, firmitas and venustas, the Latin words that Vitruvius used,
as commodity, firmness and delight.
Now, commodity and firmness come directly from commoditas and firmitas, that's quite
easy.
But coming from venustas to delight is more difficult,
because venustas, of course, refers to Venus, the goddess of love, etc.
Not something that Cedric would have been insensible to, he would have known the
Latin as well.
But delight, I think, for Cedric was important because of its reference to Wotton,
one of the earliest, perhaps not quite the earliest,
but one of the earliest texts in English on architecture, albeit a translation.
so he was referring to something about the history of architecture, the history of
architectural ideas
and the idea that architecture had a series of possibilities to offer
and part of those possibilities was delight and I think that was very important.
But I think there's a second reason he used the word delight
and that's because it was a challenge to a particular form of English socialistic
thinking
and Cedric of course was always on the left politically, he was an active supporter
of the Labour Party
although he had friends from across the political spectrum.
Now I think that for Cedric
delight was a challenge to the form of English socialism
encapsulated by people like J.B. Priestley, William Morris
Hugh Dalton, Stafford Cripps
who were both cabinet ministers in the Labour government
after the Second World War
which was very puritanical
and Cedric was certainly not a puritan
and so to say that something could be delightful
or it could engender the light,
was a challenge to what would otherwise have become,
was, I think, a very powerful form of socialist thinking.
Cedric wasn't, he didn't accept convention.
He would always challenge something if he thought it was wrong,
even if his political beliefs were closer to Hugh Dalton than Margaret Thatcher.
I think there are a number of ways or explanations
for Cedric being really influential.
One is that I think the projects, both built and unbuilt, is a formidable body of
work.
And it is, of course, available.
It's been available through publications more or less since it started.
Both publications about architecture.
He was obviously close to Architectural Design Magazine.
There are various books and monographs published about him.
So I think that's one reason.
There is a formidable body of work that covers quite a wide range of what architects
have to think about.
Another reason, I think, is that he had a very powerful network of friends and
associates.
Now, David Alford, who was one of his closest friends, if not his closest architect
friend,
built an enormous amount.
And in some ways, I think Cedric was the counterpart to David.
David wanted to build.
That was his raison d'etre, and he built some formidably good buildings of their
day,
and quite a lot of them.
Cedric I think was much less interested in building he was much more interested
in the possibilities of ideas that architectural designs could engender I
think another of the people who said Rick worked with closely and also had a
formidable built body of work many by other architects was the engineer Frank
newbie so Cedric was right at the heart of an architectural world that was
making a lot of buildings he was right at the heart of an architectural
publishing world and of course he was also associated with education. Students would
troop to go and see him even if he wasn't formally teaching them and quite often he
would. You know
he made himself available. You had to be polite, you had to ask, you had to go
through the formal
stages but it was very unusual for him to refuse to see someone point blank and I
think there were
also the active teaching roles he had not least here at the Architectural
Association. So I think
his ideas got out there in a number of different ways. I think it's a very difficult
question to
answer whether Cedric really wanted to build because I think if he had he would have
built
more. I think that he was interested in those buildings he wanted to build which is
not a very
large number and I think he was very interested in how you made the Avery for
example. I think
he was very interested in some of the smaller projects that did get built. I think
he was very
interested in the InterAction Centre, particularly when the Fun Palace didn't go
ahead. But I think
he would love to have built the Fun Palace, as would Joan Littlewood. The
InterAction Centre was
one of the built projects that Cedric made in the 1970s. It was in a part of Kentish
Town,
then quite a poor part called, it was in a part of North London, then quite a poor
part called
Kentish Town. And the idea was that you could create a series of containers or
frames in which
all sorts of different things could happen. Some of them could be directly social,
maybe a bit
cultural, maybe a bit educational, guided and unguided. I think Cedric was very
interested
in setting up possibilities and allowing people to take their own path, but to give
them various
opportunities or options for finding something out, educating themselves, having a
bit of fun,
meeting other people. And that was what the InterAction Centre was about, I think,
in essence,
was to provide a frame in which people could do all sorts of different things,
sometimes self-guided, sometimes on their own, sometimes communal.
I think the InterAction Centre related to the Fun Palace in a number of ways.
First of all, it clearly wasn't as ambitious.
The Fun Palace was an extraordinary conception that came from Cedric and from Joan
Liverwood,
who was obviously a very important influence in it.
The InterAction Centre provided some of the possibilities that the Fun Palace would
have provided.
I don't think the InterAction Centre would have been what it was
without the work that went into the Fun Palace beforehand.
I don't think we see enough of Cedric in the built environment today.
I think that a lot of what he said for much of his career is really important,
which is that architects should think about the time of their buildings,
the life cycle of their buildings,
and they shouldn't try and make a monument that is made now for all eternity.
One of Cedric's most important themes, I think, was about time.
Time was very important for Cedric. The concept of time was very important for
Cedric.
And I think that one of the things he was critical of other architects for
was imposing their spatial imaginations, as I think he termed it,
and not much else on their clients,
with very little to explain why their spatial imaginations were better than anyone
else's.
Now, for Cedric, I think he could imagine in space, very definitely,
something like the Thinkbelt is an extraordinary conception of the way you use a
piece of space,
quite a large piece of space in that case.
But he was also, and this is I think the essence, part of the essence of what Cedric
was about,
he could also imagine in time.
He could imagine how something might evolve over time
and he could imagine how it might have a life, it might have a beginning and an end.
And I think that to Cedric was really, really important
and I think it's an absolutely fundamental part of what he was about.
The InterAction Centre was a building that Cedric had always conceived as having a
fixed life.
He didn't know exactly how long it would be, but I think he probably, when it was
built,
wouldn't have thought it would last 30 years, let's say.
But it was listed. In Britain, there are historic buildings laws,
which mean that if a building is in danger and it is of real merit,
it can be listed after as little as 10 years.
And the InterAction Centre, on a piece of land that was becoming more valuable,
this was probably the early to mid-1990s, was listed.
Now, it was quite clearly a building, a structure of extraordinary importance,
but whether it needed to be preserved for that importance to continue is another
matter.
And I was working in building design at the time,
and the editor, Paul Finch, saw this press release from English Heritage or whoever
it was,
saying the new listed buildings are including the InterAction Centre.
So Paul called Cedric up and said, Cedric, I've got very bad news.
And Cedric said, what's that?
The InterAction Centre, it's listed.
And Paul could almost feel Cedric's immediate pleasure,
but then Cedric had to regather himself,
and after, at a sharp intake of breath, he said, but that's awful!
So I think it was something that Cedric was very ambiguous about.
he was in one sense very pleased, in another sense it went against the law of
philosophy, what he stood for.
Cedric was very interested in demolition.
And there was a moment, again I think it must have been in the mid-1990s,
when new building regulations were introduced in Britain.
I think they're called Construction, Design and Management, CONDAM.
And part of that was that architects, when they were designing buildings,
would have to show how they would be demolished.
This was partly a safety thing, so that someone coming in at some future point
would know that you couldn't do this without the building pinging or something.
So Cedric was very interested in Condemn
because he thought it would make architects feel much more responsible
for the process of demolition as well as construction.
I don't think there are enough traces of Cedric and his ideas
in the physical environment,
but there are lots of opportunities for making them.
I think if we talk about the Magnet Project,
which was one of the last major projects that Cedric made
with his assistant, Keiichi, in the mid-1990s.
He proposed, I think it was 12 temporary fixed-life structures,
lightweight, almost, well, they were certainly prefabricated up to a point,
that would occupy misused or underused or even abused parts of London.
Shaftesbury, I knew, was one.
There were also some suburban locations.
I think there was one over the North Circular Road in North London.
and these were taking those bits of leftover space
that neither the development industry nor the planning law
nor other forms of urban management and maintenance can deal with
and what Cedric was doing was saying these can be first of all used,
secondly they can be used constructively
and thirdly they can be used delightfully.
You can use them in such a way that you overcome problems,
that you deal with something that is otherwise an inconvenience.
There was a story that Will also told me some years ago, which was that when Will
was working
for Cedric, Cedric would say, well, the problem with buildings is that you have to
walk around
them.
And Will told me that story in the context of the Peckham Library in South London.
And he said one of the reasons it has a very small footprint on the ground and then
a few
very slender, delicate columns was because he wanted to deal with Cedric's comment
about
buildings being an inconvenience.
You had to walk around them.
He wanted to allow people to take their natural desire line route without having the
inconvenience of walking around a building.
So in some ways, I suppose, Peckham Library is one of the very few traces of the way
Cedric used to think about buildings that we could see.
But I think it's more that I would look at these parts, these sort of leftover
pieces of space in urban, suburban contexts,
the interstices between a road junction or a bit of railway embankment or something
like that,
which is otherwise wasted space, that Cedric would always have thought about
and would probably have found some sort of constructive use for.
So I think we can see Cedric's influence in his absence rather than in his presence.
But the fact that he did make these proposals,
and I think Magnet is one of the most significant of that line of Cedric's thinking,
makes one think well actually what we do need is not necessarily Cedric to come back
but to think
about well how could we learn from what he did to make better use of these sorts of
spaces.
I think one of the reasons why we don't have enough traces of Cedric's thinking in
the built
environment is because we have become so obsessed with the value of buildings, the
financial value
of buildings and also that buildings have to do something that can be defined with
great precision.
Now, Cedric, I think, always would have challenged both those assumptions.
I don't think he would have denied them completely.
He wasn't an anarchist.
He wasn't a communist.
So he accepted the notion of money and capital and value.
And he also certainly accepted the fact that there was a need to do certain things
with
certain sorts of buildings.
But I think he would have denied that buildings can only exist if they fulfill those
criteria.
So I think the general way in which law and finance and the economy has worked has
made
it very difficult to take some of these lessons from what Cedric was offering and to
make
constructive use of them.
You would almost only be able to do some of these things with some sort of
philanthropic
funding.
Enabling was a very important concept for Cedric.
I think that what he meant by enabling, again it looks like a simple word but no
word that
Cedric used in that way was ever simple. He was interested in how people can make
their
lives better, not necessarily in forcing them to do things in a particular way, and
that's
one of the reasons he was critical of the sort of puritanical streak of English
socialism.
He wanted people to have the opportunities to find out for themselves. So enabling
was
providing, this is in very crude terms, a frame for people to collect, curate and
develop
their own experiences and their own knowledge. It could be direct, it could not
directed,
these experiences could be as it were offered to people but there wouldn't be
coercion that
you must do this or you must do that or you must do these things in a particular
order.
It would be an offering rather than a forcing I think. So enabling was about
allowing people
to better themselves by the opportunities that could be created.
And architecture was a small part of that,
and it was a small part and a very significant part
because it could be negative.
It could stop that process of enabling.
It could force you to walk on a different route
because the building was in the way, for example, in very simple terms.
Whereas a building that Cedric designed,
whether it was a fun palace or the InterAction Centre or magnet or whatever,
would actually enable a much greater series of possibilities
without forcing you to take them.
I think it's very difficult to say what Cedric's most significant project is.
If I were forced, I'd probably say The Fun Palace,
because I do think that's one that he worked on for a very long time.
He had an inspirational client collaborator in Joan Littlewood with it.
It was, I think, it came out of a particular moment.
Joan, of course, was a fantastic, radical theatre director
who had made theatre the most significant, not her alone,
but she was part of a group of directors
who had made theatre the most avant-garde aspect of British culture
in the 1940s, 50s and 60s.
And what she wanted in the Fun Palace
was something that was both...
She called it a university of the streets or some such phrase,
that she wanted to expand the capacity that theatre and performance had,
but not to limit what it would offer to theatre and performance.
It would move into other things as well.
It could be a library, it could be a gallery.
It would be something quite magnificent.
And of course it was virtually buildable.
I mean it was designed to a point where it could be built.
There was maybe one or two technological issues that would need resolution
but there was no doubt that they could have been resolved.
And there were also, I think in some cases, at least two sites
where it was very seriously considered.
So it was a long-running project, a very significant project,
and one that was probably pretty close to coming off,
and I think it's a great tragedy that it didn't.
Well, I think it resonates both as an idea
that I think there are a lot of people,
particularly someone like Hansel de Colbrist, the curator,
who looks back at the Fun Palace as perhaps not the perfect model,
but as an inspiration to how you might think about a gallery for the 21st century.
And some years ago, in my work at the Royal Academy of Art,
we asked a series of people to talk about what they thought was the most significant
building in London.
Hans Ulrich was one of them, and he picked the Fun Palace.
And he gave an extraordinarily inspiring address about it.
So I think, yes, it does resonate, not perhaps entirely within architecture,
but Cedric would never have seen it purely as an architectural device.
it was a social device, a cultural device.
Another one I find absolutely intriguing,
and again very, very far-reaching, is the Pottery Sink Belt.
And that, I think, came about at a particular moment,
at the point where the British higher education system was expanding.
But it was expanding in a very particular way.
The old universities, Oxford and Cambridge,
were building new colleges and the existing colleges were expanding.
but basically replicating the same sort of buildings and spaces
and certainly replicating the same sort of education
that they had been offering for decades, if not hundreds of years.
The new universities of that period, like York and East Anglia,
were on suburban sites.
Some of them were well-designed, some of them less well-designed,
but they were all just outside cities
that narrowly avoided getting a university in the Middle Ages.
You could rewind the history of England and you would not be entirely surprised if
York or Norwich had had a university in 1500 because they were both very important
cities in the Middle Ages.
The Thinkbelt was an attempt to get entirely away from the conventions of university
work, what universities were considered to be about,
and to offer something that was perhaps more in tune with what was necessary at the
time.
It reused a declining bit of industrial infrastructure,
the old potteries, which of course is where Cedric came from,
where he was born, and an area he knew very well,
but even in the early 1960s, industry was moving out.
It reused industrial infrastructure,
so the railway tracks would have been part of the system of transportation of goods
and people,
it would have had the latest in information technology because Cedric was very
interested
in that in how you could use technology to minimize the need the expense of building
if you
could put people in touch with each other or put people in touch with ideas without
a building I
think you would always have thought that was preferable to having to provide a
building which
can only do it in a rather crude way and I think also the Thinkbelt was important
because it would
have been a symbol for a form of knowledge, a form of education that was very
important,
mainly technical education, but did not require the English class structure of
public school,
Oxford and Cambridge, Inns of Court, House of Commons, House of Lords, which I think
was still the model of how English society worked.
The Thinkbelt reached a very wide audience by being published in New Society
magazine.
His editor, Paul Barker, was an extremely wide-ranging, insightful journalist,
editor.
And among other things, he published a weekly column by Rainer Bannum.
And Paul is not an architect.
He thinks very much about the relationship between space, spatial environment,
physical environment, and social opportunity.
And this, of course, was right in the territory Cedric was thinking about with the
Thinkbelt.
So a lot of work went into the Thinkbelt.
I'm not sure whether there was a client, an assumed client, or whether there was
even
someone who was paying the bills, but Paul, through New Society, gave it a big
readership.
New Society at that time had a big circulation.
It was a very influential magazine of ideas, and I think anyone who wanted to be
informed
read it.
And although it was sort of on the left, it was never doctrinaire on the left, and
it
was very critical of certain aspects of left-wing as well as of right-wing thinking.
It was a very interesting journal of ideas.
And I think that the Thinkbelt was absolutely up its street.
I remember when I was asked to talk about it some years ago,
I looked at the date of the magazine that's published
and it was about the time of my second birthday.
So I was being asked to talk about something
that had been in effect designed certainly before I was conscious of it.
I think Cedric's main agenda,
the things that preoccupied him most,
were how could you set up physical and social and informational structures
that allow people to fulfil themselves.
This is very much about enabling, a word that Cedric used a lot.
Now, buildings architecture had possibilities for enabling
and it could do both by providing a physical frame within which certain things could
happen,
in other words, a building, what we might think of as a building.
But architecture as a way of thinking could also enable new ways of thinking.
Not about architecture itself.
Architecture is very much both the metaphorical and the physical frame.
The fulfilment was never the building, the image of the building, the consequence of
that building.
It was actually what the building offered you that would allow you to go beyond
where you were before.
And I think that was very much one of his central preoccupations at least.
And I think that is also closely related to his concept of time.
If you're enabling people, it implies a chronology, it implies a time,
because enabling is a process that doesn't happen in a nanosecond.
It happens over a period of time.
So the process of enabling was something that related to Cedric's interest in time.
And I think when he was designing buildings or thinking about what sort of buildings
might be appropriate,
he would think well how long can this structure continue to be an enabling
structure?
So for example in the Potteries Thinkbelt all the structures were of relatively
short life
because you didn't know what technology would be 15 years down the line.
You might have a good idea of what it might be in 5 years, possibly even in 10
years, but beyond that,
so well within a working career, technology might change several times and in
unforeseen ways.
So the idea of being fixed life was tied up with the need to enable.
There are lots of anecdotes about Cedric.
He was a very gregarious, very ebullient character.
There are several.
One is, and it was told to me by both participants, David Alford and Cedric Price.
And David, it's fair to say, moved to the political right from being on the left as
a young man.
young man. And Cedric of course stayed on the left although he was always quite
critical
of certain left wing positions or conventionally left wing positions. And David was
also quite
a combative character. He liked picking an argument. And David and Cedric were
having
a drink somewhere which was not an uncommon occurrence and they started talking
about
politics and David was very provocative particularly with people he thought were
left wing and
and he enjoyed the argument.
And he, probably having bought a rather fine bottle of wine,
which he would also do,
he said, Cedric, well, how do you think, in a socialist society,
we would divide up wine?
And Cedric just said, ration it,
at which point they came to blows.
I think Cedric was very generous,
and he was generous in a particular way.
He was generous with his time and he was generous with his intellect.
and he was also, if you like, too generous with his cigars and brandy.
And that meant a huge amount to me when I was in my 20s, 30s,
and that Cedric would be there,
not just because he was a very significant and very well-known figure,
but because he would actually engage with what I was interested in.
And there was one time when Cedric had offered me use of his library,
or the run of his library with some books
that he thought would interest me in my work on F.R.S. York.
was very useful and I was upstairs in the white room and we would Cedric
started work early in the morning when he wasn't having breakfast 730 830 so I
got there early in the morning and Cedric was there cooking breakfast if I
remember rightly always in the office and the white room had a little baby
bedding stove and and he would if you were very lucky he would cook you
breakfast if you had breakfast you generally had to have brandy in a cigar
as well. And there were also the books. So I started and I looked at these books and
thought, oh, this is going to be quite a lot of work to go through this and I want
to get
on with it. And Cedric said, well, would you like a glass of brandy? This was 8.30
in the
morning. I said, well, actually, Cedric, not today, if you don't mind. He said,
well, I'm
going to have one. And I said, yes, please do. And then he went downstairs to his
office
and 20 minutes later he came back and said, are you sure you won't have a brandy?
And I said, no, actually, Cedric, I'd really rather not just at the moment, maybe
later.
So he went down, 20 minutes later, he's up again, what about a cigar?
And I said, no, Cedric, really, I'm actually trying to work.
And then he went down again.
And then 20 minutes after that, he was back again, glass of brandy, cigar.
He said, well, if you're not going to have a brandy or a cigar, I'm going to have
both.
And I realised that it was going to be very difficult to do this work
because Cedric actually wanted to chat.
So there was a great generosity and a great sense of fun with him.
I mean, there were times when we talked about very serious things,
and of course there were times when we talked about things
which were not inherently fun,
but there was always a sense with Cedric of optimism,
and I think that was really important,
and that came through his personality,
I think it came through his relationships with other people,
you know, his friends, people who worked with him,
that there was always a sense of fun,
as well as a sense of a serious purpose underneath the fun,
or connected to the fun.
The white room was a space at the top of Cedric's office in Alpha Place, which was
painted white.
Floor, ceiling, walls.
It was relatively sparsely furnished.
There was a table, there were a few chairs, there was a little stove and I think a
fridge and a sink.
It must have been at some stage fitted out as a small flat for the rest of the
offices.
I'm not sure that Cedric ever used it like that, but he certainly used it to do some
entertaining.
And it was a sort of sacrosanct space.
It was where work was not done.
The other floors were where people worked.
The White Room was where you went for meetings, conversation,
where your brain would certainly be picked.
It was not project-based work, I suppose.
It was intellectual work of a more abstract nature.
I don't think the White Room was a sacred place.
I don't think Cedric thought in those terms.
It was certainly a sanctuary.
It was a place where he would go.
I think he spent a certain amount of time there on his own,
reading, reading newspaper.
He never had a telephone there, that was the other thing, that it was free from
interference.
It was, yes, certainly to be invited there was quite an honour and a pleasure.
I'm sure there are people who would like to have been invited who weren't, but I
also
think that Cedric, if someone wrote to him or telephoned him and gave him enough to
interest
him in them, they would be invited to have a conversation.
That would probably be in the White Room.
For Cedric the relationship between people as individuals and institutions was
extremely
important.
He wasn't an anarchist.
He thought that there needed to be institutions.
He thought that there was knowledge that should be made available.
It shouldn't be done on an exclusive basis or an elitist basis.
But you weren't, I think in Cedric's view, born with everything you needed to know.
You didn't know, you hadn't met everyone you might need to meet or would benefit
from meeting.
So there was a role for certain sorts of institutions in society.
I think what made Cedric a really important thinker, and it runs through so much of
his
work, was the idea that institutions don't have to perpetuate themselves.
You create institutions for a particular purpose.
It might be educational, it might be governments, it might be informational, it
might be to
do with leisure and fun.
But they should never be open-ended in their time.
So a project like Pop-up Parliament was to try and move the idea of Parliament, or
indeed
move the idea of a democratic, organisational governing body away from some of the
older
traditions associated with it into something that was more responsive and more
appropriate
for the period it was done.
Now I personally think there's quite a lot to be said for certain sorts of
traditions
to remain, but I'm also very receptive to Cedric's ideas that certain sorts of
institutions
in particular should be limited in time.
I remember having a conversation with him about something that happened when it was
realised that there were far fewer house fires than there had been, and therefore
the fire
Brigade's role was changing because it wasn't called out to house fires as much.
And the Fire Brigade had made a play to take over the Ambulance Service, where
the Ambulance Service was increasing in its work and the Fire Brigade was
declining. In order to perpetuate the existence of an institution called the
Fire Service, it tried to take over the Ambulance Service, when in Cedric's view,
if they were going to murder a toilet, it should have been the other way around.
The ambulance service was more innovative in how it was using ambulances.
It had a need that was increasing or changing,
whereas the need for the fire brigade was declining,
in its conventional sense at least.
And I think that's part of what he was talking about with institutions,
that you don't need to feel they have to be perpetuated beyond their natural life.
Now, that's one side, I think, of what I was trying to explain in the Guardian
obituary.
The other side, I think, is very much that the test of an institution, of the value
of an institution, was the degree to which it would enable someone to improve their
own life, their own status, their own experience, their own enjoyment.
And if an institution didn't offer that, then I think he would have thought it had
no purpose.
That didn't mean that every institution had to offer equal amounts of joy, pleasure,
delight, democracy to everyone,
but they had to have a constituency of people who they were enabling to do something
better.
I think there's an important insight into how Cedric thought about institutions and
their social role
in something he wrote, I think, in the early 1980s,
which was over hot imagery in built form appears to be in inverse proportion to the
importance of the activities it houses.
And I think that sums up something about what Cedric thought about institutions that
choose to house themselves in a purely symbolic home and not thinking about the
degree of time or the capacity for enabling they had.
when I was thinking about the Thinkbelt for the supercrit I looked at the
publication of the
architectural review used to do a sort of review of buildings of the year and I did
two or three
years either side of the think Thinkbelt on that to see what what contemporary
British architecture
was in effect and one of them was a very beautiful building for Newhall College in
Cambridge designed
by Chamberlain Powell and Bong who were good architects they designed the Barbican
Centre
and Golden Lane, but it is absolutely what Cedric would scathingly have called Roman
architecture with 13 amp sockets. And I think by that he meant an architecture that
could
have been conceived 2,000 years earlier, and it was only redeemed from modern use
because
somehow the technology had been inserted into it. Well, Pop-Up Parliament, I think,
was
a project that Cedric did in the middle of the 1960s. Again, I think it was in
association
with New Society magazine and Paul Barker, the editor.
And what it was, was a way of thinking about how a parliament could act
outside or not contained by the very, very heavy symbolism
of the British Houses of Parliament,
which was a huge building, not that old,
well, the oldest parts were very old,
but most of what you see in the Houses of Parliament
is mid to even late 19th century.
And in living memory, certainly in the 1960s, it had been bombed.
the House of Commons, the Chamber of the House of Commons was destroyed.
And Winston Churchill, as Prime Minister, said,
we must rebuild it exactly as it was,
because that is how we will continue our democratic traditions.
And I think what Paul Barker and Cedric were trying to get away from
was that sort of replicating of tradition
and that sort of continuation of tradition,
as opposed to what they might have called essence,
which was democracy and democratic action.
Now could a different sort of building, a different sort of spatial system, spatial
relations and of information flows offer that in a different way?
And I think that's what pop-up parliament was about.
It didn't need to be a huge stone-built building that wouldn't move.
And in some ways, and I'm not sure that they would have accepted this, but it was
going back to the roots of parliament, which was when it was peripatetic.
Parliament used to travel around the country and would meet wherever the king called
it.
And it was only in the 14th, 15th century that Parliament became fixed and
associated with one particular place.
And it was only in the 19th century that it got a purpose-designed building.
So in fact, what they were doing was actually looking back, perhaps, in some ways,
or what they were doing had some analogies with the history of Parliament itself.
I'm not sure that for Cedric the historical resonances would have been the most
important thing.
I think for Cedric the really important thing would have been to use the most
appropriate technology
in building materials and information technology
to allow democracy to act better,
particularly by allowing elected, mandated members of parliament
to do their work in a more open and a more efficient way.
Well, Cedric certainly challenged traditional architectural aesthetics.
He was incredibly knowledgeable about architecture of the past,
and this is something that a lot of people don't understand.
you could mention a relatively obscure 18th century country house.
Cedric would know it, he would have been there,
he would be able to draw it,
he would tell you a lot about its history.
So he had a phenomenal knowledge of the traditions of architecture,
but he was never uncritical of them,
and he certainly rejected any sense
that what had worked in the 18th century or even the 19th century
or even the early 20th century
would have worked for the later 20th century or into the 21st century.
So he was always challenging the traditions and the conventions
but from a position of knowing what they were,
and knowing what they had achieved,
and knowing what their strengths were as well as their weaknesses.
So was Cedric rejecting conventional architectural aesthetics?
Yes, I think he was.
I think Cedric's comment about over-hot imagery
being in inverse proportion to the importance of the activity it houses
is a summing up of his rejection or his attack
on the conventions of architectural aesthetics.
For Cedric, aesthetics came from a way of thinking and a way of doing and a way of
enabling.
I think he was a phenomenal artist.
I think his visual sense was extraordinary.
I think you only need to look at the way he built up his imagery,
using drawings, using photocopies, using rubber stamps.
Everything was extraordinarily precise and beautifully worked out.
And I think that's one reason why a lot of contemporary artists are so interested in
Cedric,
because he was a profoundly visual and aesthetic thinker,
but he did so largely outside or beyond the conventions of the discipline of
architecture.
I think the relevance of Cedric now comes in several different parts.
I think the body of work that he produced is still extraordinarily important,
and even if some of it's now 50 years old,
there are still important and interesting things we can find and we can look at.
And that is a challenge to how we think about architecture.
And I think that will always be there.
Cedric's, I think, perhaps his most lasting contribution,
certainly one of the most significant contributions he made,
is to show that you could always challenge convention.
You never had to accept it.
So I think that's something that architects could actually do an awful lot more of
and indeed sacred clients very often.
I think, so the body of work still has extraordinary relevance.
I think there are people who worked with Cedric and knew Cedric well
who are producing very important work.
Coolhouse is certainly one of them.
And I don't think you could reduce his practice to Cedric's or Cedric's to his,
but I think his ability to bring together pieces of information from outside
architecture
and to develop programmes as much as buildings owes quite a lot to Cedric
and I think in some ways that's a continuation of ways of thinking that Cedric set
up.